Hello everyone, in this video we're gonna talk about ensemble method and especially random forest.
So what is an ensemble?
If you hear ensemble, you might imagine this kind of image.
So individual instrument players can make some sound in the music.
However, the sound characteristic and spectrum can be limited by one instrument alone.
But if you have a collection of these different types of instruments, you can make very rich and flavorable musical sound.
And that's the ensemble.
So this kind of analogy can apply to machine learning model.
So for example, decision tree can be a weak learner.
However, if they are aggregated in certain ways, they can be much better.
So here is an intuition why the collection of machine learning model can be better.
Well, let's say we have some problem to solve in the general public community.
If you sample people that has the same race, same gender, same age group, and same kind of background, it's likely to have only represent those kind of people.
The other hand, if you have a diverse people that has a different gender, different age group, and race, and background, it's likely to have more representative of the different groups and then therefore we are likely to make a better decision.
Okay, so diversity is great.
Then how can we make our models diverse?
One idea might be maybe we can train our models on different subsets of data.
So training model on different random subset of data is called bagging.
You can think about like putting different data set into bag and then make the model trained on this bag of the data.
Well, but actually the name is not because they put the data into bags, but...
The full name is a bootstrap aggregation.
So bootstrap aggregation is like this.
You have different ways to random sample the data.
So first step would be a randomly sample subset of training data with the replacement.
So we can use the replacement.
That means we can sample the same data that we already sampled.
So let's say you can sample this yellow sections out of this whole data.
and you can also have this overlaps like this.
So that's a bootstrap process.
And then we can grow a tree on this selected data.
So tree number 1 and tree number 2, tree number 3, tree number 4, etc.
And in general, we don't let this tree prune because they may become similar to each other.
However, it is also possible in practice that we can grow prune the tree and then ensemble them.
Alright, and then after growing this tree to each different subset of data, we can ensemble them.
So ensemble method in regression, the famous method is just averaging the result and for classification we can use the voting method.
Another bonus by doing bagging is we can use the auto bag error.
So auto bag error is kind of validation error that we can test our fitted tree.
that was trained on these yellow chunks.
Then we can test on this the rest of the data that we didn't select to train on.
So let's talk about random forest.
So random forest has another added idea to the bagging.
So bagging classifier alone can give some performance boost because we can diversify our models by training on the random sample data subsets.
And in random forest on top of that
We also have some process of decorrelation.
That means we random sample the features and have the model fitted to this subset of the features instead of whole features.
So why is it called the decorrelation?
Because if we have the same features all the time to grow the trees, even though the data subsets are slightly different, the individual tree might have the same structure of splitting in the same orders of
so on.
So if you have a random sampling of features, individual trees grown on the subset of the data and subset of features will be likely to have a different structure from each other.
So that is why it is called a decorrelation.
So having this bagging and decorrelation together, the whole algorithm is called the random forest.
Okay great I get that why the random sampling features might help, then how do I randomly sample these features?
A rule of thumb is the square root method.
So when we have 100 features in the data, we will select 10 features in the data subset.
Here are the results of random forest classifiers.
The green line shows that we had a square root method for selecting features versus the red curve means a random forest using all samples.
So essentially that's the bagging.
So you can see some increased performance when we de-correlate the trees.
or use a smaller number of features.
Here is another result showing the power of angsangbol.
So this green star point is actually a single tree test performance.
And then as you can see, as we increase the number of trees in the angsangbol, it generally goes up and then at a certain point, they kind of behave similar.
So this blue curve, for example, is a random forest test error.
And this red curve is a bagging test error.
So both the random forest and the bagging method, they are ensembleing methods and they increase the performance a lot compared to just a single tree.
However, as you can see, decolonizing trees make it a little better than just bagging, just random sampling the data.
You can also see the out-of-bag test error.
So these are kind of validation error during the training process.
And random forests also have a cool feature.
It has a built-in feature importance.
So in SQL library you can pull out feature importance after fitting the random forest model in the data.
Oftentimes this is useful because you can figure out some feature importance and then use it as a feature selection.
So even if you want to use some different model you can still use random forest to do the feature selection and then you can build some more serious model on top of it.
So that can be a handy tool.
Alright, so far we talked about some basics of random forest, what their definition is, and why they are useful, and what kind of mechanism they work on.
And next video, we're going to talk about another angsangbuk method called boosting.