Hello everyone.
In this video, we're going to talk about support vector machine with the kernel tricks.
So just a brief recap, we talked about hard margin classifier, which goal is to maximize its margin, which is the distance between the hyperplane and the support vectors.
And then, in case we had inseparable data like this, we simply added the slack variable epsilon to all this.
data points and then this epsilon just specify how much they deviates from the margin.
So like this for red points and then this amount for different blue points here.
And these slack variables need to satisfy two conditions such as it has to be no negative value and then we also define the c parameter which gives an idea how much of error budget we have.
Also we mentioned that
Sometimes the data can be not possible to use one hyperplane to separate the data.
So in that case, we need to use some special trick called the kernel trick, which will be the subject of this video.
Before we go on what the kernels are, let's think about this.
So in support vector classifier, which is another name for submargin classifier, we mentioned that we have to satisfy all these conditions.
And
this part is the formula for the hyperplane.
Let's call it f .
And then this beta zero and beta one and all the way to the beta p are the coefficients for this equation.
And the optimizer will find the values for these coefficients.
Now we can ask ourselves, why do we call SVM as a non-parametric method when we do see these parameters in the equation?
18.
That's very much related to the use of Connors.
You might notice that I use the term SVC, which is a Supervector Classifier, versus SVM, Supervector Machine.
It's not very important, but Supervector Machine generally refers to some generalization of Supervector Classifier, whereas Supervector Classifier usually refers to the Soft Margin Classifier.
In SKLUN, they use a different algorithm.
SVC uses a lip linear.
It's very much similar to the optimization algorithm that we use in logistic regression.
Whereas this SVM uses a libSVM algorithm which is specially made for SVM and this algorithm uses the kernels.
Alright, so let's talk about what the kernels are.
So this is again hard margin classifier and this is soft margin classifier and this is the formula for the hyperplane.
We're going to introduce a different math formula which is equivalent to this formula f .
However, we'll skip the derivation and just show the result.
So using the inner product, it is known that this formula f can be rewritten to this formula.
And this is a dot product.
So if you have xi', then this is dot product between the point i' and point i.
And this dot product represents the linear corner.
Oftentimes, we will call it as K kernel, xi and xi'.
That product again is a linear kernel.
So essentially, this is same as this one.
However, when we implement the algorithm, it will have a different time complexity.
So for example, the SVC that uses a linear library will have time complexity of number of data point times number of features.
And if we use the libSVM and solve for linear data, then it's going to take more time.
It's going to have SVM with linear corner.
It's going to take n squared times p. So by using kernel, it doesn't seem it's useful for the linear data.
However, the kernel method shines when it comes to complex data.
So let's have a look.
When we have this type of data that's not possible to separate by linear hyperplane, what we want to do is this.
So let's say a simple example, we have a data that's not linearly separable.
So in the one-dimensional, the hyperplane will be just a point.
So we need two hyperplanes in order to separate it perfectly.
However, it's not possible.
So the trick is,
We can add one dimension here and then now we can separate this perfectly with this one hyperplane So adding one more dimension is a key and it's called the kernel trick.
So again, this data is not separable In 2D using linear hyperplane So what we do is we add the third dimension.
So this is a G by the way, and this is Maybe we can call it X and Y So we're gonna introduce G and maybe X here and Y here
And now we can see that this data is separable with the hyperplane like this.
Adding one more dimension means that we want to make a higher order terms in the function.
Okay, so we have a p number of features in the data and then we can add a higher order terms in order to make extra dimensions to separate the data points, which was previously not separable in the linear fashion.
So we can add higher order terms like this, but then, naively, what happens is that
Now our optimization need to find all these parameter values for the higher order terms Which might be a lie if you add even more higher order terms And as well as if you have a large number of features It's going to be a problem like we saw in the polynomial regression So instead of adding directly higher order terms we can use a kernel trick instead So let's make a use of this inner product We can create a function kernel function k that has this form this is the
dot product and then represent a first order terms.
And by having a constant plus this dot product to the order of d, we can create the polynomial function for the high order terms.
And then we can generalize our function to be a form that has these corners.
So let's have a look when we have this type of data that might involve a nonlinear decision boundary.
We can use polynomial kernel that we just saw.
By having polynomial kernel, we can have this type of decision boundary.
Shows the data result when we had the d equals 2 for polynomial kernels.
Which nicely separates these blue points and the red points by adding another dimension to the data.
There are other types of kernels and another very famous one is called the radial kernel or sometimes called the radial basis functional kernel or RBF for short.
And it takes this form, this kind of Gaussian shape kernel.
defines the RBF corner and the result is like this.
So it's like a round shape.
Basis corner will be able to separate this data into three blobs.
So having corner is great.
You can solve some complex data.
However, we need to think ahead what kind of kernels that we should use.
So when it's a linear separable, you can see that we don't need any fancy kernels.
Just a linear kernel or linear SVM or SVC that does not use a kernel at all will solve perfectly.
Whereas RBF corner is fancy corner so the radial basis corner can also solve the problem depending on how the data look like.
So this data was generated by a blob data and linear is approvable.
So it was both linear SVM and RBF-SVM worked well.
You know different types of data like this, this shape like yin and yang or moon shape in sklon, they look like this type of data usually.
The linear SVM doesn't work very well.
However, the radial basis corner did well on this.
Other corners did not do well for this type of data.
How about this circular donut shape of data?
Linear SVM did not do very well as you can expect.
But radial kernel is perfect for this type of data because the data shape is radial.
So now you can see that
The choice of kernel strongly depends on the pattern of the data.
So although the kernel is very convenient for this nonlinear data, it requires the user to think about what the data looks like and guess what the best kernel would be.