Alright, so let's talk about how well my model fits.
So we're going to look at the numbers R squared value and adjusted R squared.
These are metrics for how well the model fits.
Adjusted R squared is actually same as R squared except that it also takes number of features in top count.
However, when the number of samples are much larger than number of features in the model, these two numbers are essentially the same.
So let's derive R squared as a measure of model fit.
When do we know that model has a good fit?
From the least squared method that we used to determine our coefficient values, we know that model has a good fit when we have a squared error is minimized.
So again, we can use MSC or RSS.
RSS is a residual thermal squares.
It's nothing but same as MSC without the averaging factor.
So we define this quantity and we know that if this quantity is minimized, we know the model has a good fit.
However, there is a little bit of problem with this metric.
One is that this value can be arbitrarily large depending on our unit of the
target variable.
And also if we have a different set of data, this quantity will be different.
So we want to normalize by something similar error measure that has same kind of unit.
So what would be a good way to do that?
We can define a benchmark model, say y equals y mean, and then we can compare how good is my error from my model.
y equals beta 0 plus beta 1 x.
Compared to the error of my benchmark model, which is y equals y min, so we're gonna define another quantity called the TSS, total sum of squares, that actually quantifies the error between my null model and my training data points.
So with that, we can define a dimensionless quantity.
by dividing RSS by TSS.
So this is a quantity essentially telling that what's the ratio of the error from my model to the error from the null model or benchmark model.
So this can be a good quantity that measures how my model fits compared to my null model.
We also want our quantity or R-squared value to be higher when
when my model fits better.
And if you see, RSS goes down when the model fits better.
So we're going to flip the sign.
We're going to just subtract this quantity from 1.
Then actually it becomes the definition of R squared.
So let's take a moment and think about what values R squared can take.
All right.
So we're gonna think about two extreme cases.
So one extreme case is that when my RSS is 0, that means my model fits perfectly all of the data points, which will never happen in practice.
But let's think that my model is so good that all the data points are on my model's line.
Then this term goes to 0, and my R-squared value will go 1.
So that's one extreme.
Can R-squared go 1?
larger than 1.
R-squared value cannot be larger than 1 because RSS cannot be negative, right?
The another extreme case is that my model is actually just as good as my null model y equals y mean.
In that case, my RSS value will be same as TSS.
So this goes to 1.
Then my R squared will go to zero.
Can R squared value go negative?
Yes, it can.
In practice, if you use a package to fit your regression line, it will almost never happen.
But in case your model is this bad, like this, the slope is totally wrong.
And then it might have RSS that's larger than TSS.
Then this R squared value can go negative.
For simple linear regression, this may not happen, but as you might see later, in a more complex model, sometimes the model can fit worse than the baseline.
So remember that R-squared can go negative as well.
Alright, so we saw that R-squared value could be a good measure of how my model fits.
However, you have to be careful when you interpret the value from your summary table.
Let's take an example where we
might want a model that takes a form of ax and there is no intercept.
Why would we want to do that?
So let's have a look at the intercept value.
It's a negative value and that means my sales price will go negative when my living space is zero.
That doesn't make a lot of sense.
So maybe instead of having this uninterpretable intercept, maybe we want to have a model that has no intercept.
And then, yeah that sounds good.
My sales price of house should be zero when the living space is zero.
So let's take a fit and look at the summary table.
We have a square fit living coefficient which is similar to the previous value which is good.
But then we suddenly see R-squared value has gone up.
What does that mean?
Does it mean our new model y equals ax is better than our old model ax plus b?
Well, not necessarily.
If you look at carefully, you're going to see uncensored next to the r squared.
What does that mean?
It turns out that this r squared value is calculated such that RSS of our new model, this guy,
and then divide by TSS of the new null model which is not y equals y mean but now our new null model is y equals 0.
So this goes to here and then the total sum of squares from y equals 0 will be way higher.
Therefore, the R-squared value ...
can be much larger than the previous one.
So if you want to compare apple to apple how my new model is doing in terms of the error, you can just directly calculate RSS for our new model.
Let's say y equals ax and then compare with the previous model RSS y equals ax plus b.
Then you're gonna see this RSS is larger than this one.
But the value that it gives here in the summary table is a little bit deceptive.