Okay, so let's talk about how significant the coefficient values are.
So when do you say the coefficient values are significant?
And conversely, when can we say that the coefficient value is not significant?
So think about this, when the coefficient value is not significant, that means we picked up some kind of noise from the data and assign some value for coefficients.
when in fact the coefficient value is zero.
So when you hear coefficient value is not significant, that means the coefficient value should be actually zero.
So let's look at this coefficient value.
It's minus 4000 something and it's a 280 something.
So that looks like that's very big number, big difference from zero.
So maybe we can, can you just say my coefficient values are all significant.
So the absolute value of the coefficient value is not enough to say whether it's significant or not, because consider we change the unit of this target variable, then we can suddenly have a very small coefficient number, and it's hard to tell then whether this number should be zero or not.
So we need some comparison.
We need some way to compare whether this number is good enough or not.
And usually the standard error is a good way to tell it.
So that means if my coefficient value is maybe here, let's say mu, average of my coefficient value is here and this is zero.
And we want to know how far away is my average coefficient value.
And also we want to know how much of spread I have.
So if the spread is pretty large like this, then maybe this mean value for my coefficient isn't very real.
However, if I have this sharp distribution that essentially says my spread of my values for the coefficients are this small and this far away from
zero, then I can say with the confidence that my coefficient value is actually real.
So we're going to talk about this and all these values that shows here are good measure of those confidence or statistical significance.
So let's dive in.
So we mentioned that it is important to know the standard error or the spread of my coefficient value.
And there are different ways to get the
standard error or the spread of my coefficient value.
One is using some theory or assumption that the residual is some normal distribution with the zero mean and certain spread or variance.
Another way to do that is we just resample the data multiple times and then fit onto that data and get the coefficient value and we do that experiment multiple times.
then we can get the standard error of my coefficients and all kinds of statistical values from there.
But let's briefly talk about what this model-based method is.
So VIRAR derivation, this is called the covariance matrix, which is variance of beta zero, variance of beta one, and covariance of beta zero and beta one.
So matrix looks like this.
But however, we don't have to remember all this math.
This is given by this formula and this leads to the standard error value for intercept and slope.
It looks like this.
However, we don't have to remember all this formula.
But important thing to remember is that all of this variance or standard error value is proportional to the variance of the residual.
So that means if I have data that has a large spread like this, then it's likely that my coefficient values also have a large spread.
And also you can see that the spread of the coefficients not only depends on this variance of the residuals, but also the variance of the data itself.
This model assumes a homoscedasticity.
That means
the spread of the data is kind of homogeneous over the data.
However, if you look at our data, that looks like some kind of cone shape like this.
The residual, the spread of the residual is not homogeneous.
However, we can still assume this model and then derive the quantities that we need.
If you are not convinced by that,
the model's assumption, then maybe we can use bootstrapping method.
So bootstrapping method is resampling method.
So let's say we have data point that looks like this originally.
Then we can sample some experiment that samples some of the data point like this.
And then we can have that and then
draw another one that samples this data.
And so on.
And we can have multiple copies of this.
We can have many many samples that we want.
We can even sample the same data twice or multiple times.
It doesn't matter.
We can have some sampling with the replacement.
So let's say we have many data like that and then we can fit the coefficient values and this coefficient value will be different from this one slightly but they will be similar.
So we get all these values then we can get the mean value of this as well as the standard deviation or variance of that value.
Alright so that's how we get standard error for the coefficient values.
So let's talk about how we determine whether our coefficient values are statistically significant.
To do that, we're going to do the hypothesis testing.
With the two hypothesis, the null hypothesis say that our coefficient value is 0 and the alternate hypothesis saying that our coefficient value is not 0.
And to test that, we're going to construct a t-score which is given by this.
The t-score is standardized.
our coefficient value, estimate value, by subtracting the mean which is given by our hypothesis and the standard error of our estimated coefficient.
This is similar to G-score in normal distribution and actually when the number of samples is larger than 30, the t-distribution approximate to normal distribution so they are essentially the same most of cases.
We're going to calculate the p-value and
We can briefly review.
So let's say we have a standard normal distribution like this.
This is zero mean and has a unit variance.
And then let's say we want to have a 5% of error rate.
So that gives us critical value which defines that this area within these critical values.
plus 1.96 and minus 1.96 for standard normal distribution.
This area is 0.95 and the rest, this region and that region, the combined area would be 0.05.
So that's our error rate and this value is also called alpha.
And in standard normal distribution,
this shaded area are symmetric, so each of them is going to be 0.025 0.025 and then we're going to have p-value according to our t-score.
So whenever our t-score lies in the rejection region which is shaded in this red area,
or maybe here, then we can reject the null hypothesis.
And what is the p-value here?
p-value is this area under the curve enclosed by this t-score or this area in case the t-score was negative.
In that case, in this particular example, our p-value is smaller than the
half of the alpha.
So this green area is smaller than the rejection area and in that case, our t-score lies in the rejection region.
Therefore, we can reject the null hypothesis.
What if our t-score lied in here?
Then again, our p-value will be this big.
So when our p-value is bigger than the half of the alpha,
we cannot reject the null hypothesis.
All right, so let's see if we can reject the null hypothesis from our regression result.
So that looks like this.
When we look at the t value, it's minus 10, I'm gonna change my color, it's minus 10 sigma away from the mean and for the intercept and for the slope, it's 145 sigma away from the mean.
So that's pretty significant and as you can expect the p value is
fairly small, almost zero for two coefficients.
Therefore, we can safely reject the null hypothesis and we can conclude that our coefficient values are statistically significant.
Similarly, we can also define 95% CI, competency-inheritance for the coefficients.
To calculate that, the formula is given by this.
Mean of the coefficient plus minus two
or actually it's 1.96 times the standard error and the standard error is given here.
We can also define 95% confidence interval for the regression line.
That means 95% of time my regression line will lie within this orange shaded region.
And 95% prediction interval, which is for the sample points.
That means 95% of time the sample points will be within this blue shaded region.
This analysis can be handy when you have some outliers and these outliers may be good to remove to have better regression.
Ok, so let's talk about how we measure the error from the test data and the training data and how to compare them.
So we talked about this popular error measure so we're going to use them or one of them and let's say we have original training data that we used to use
to fit the model.
Instead of using all of them to fit the model, we're going to set aside some data.
Some portion of data is test data.
And the rest we're going to use it for training.
train set, test set, and each of them have feature and label.
So train set has feature x train and label y train.
and the test set has feature test and label test.
So using the train set, we're gonna fit the model.
So model initially had undefined coefficient values.
So we're gonna do fit and then supply our train data, X train and Y train.
And this fit function will determine the coefficient values.
And now this model internally will have optimal coefficient values.
So with that, we're gonna predict this time.
So dot predict.
And for prediction, we don't need a label.
So we're gonna put train data.
Then it becomes yprediction.
So I'm gonna put hat here, but from the training data.
We can do the similar.
with the already fitted model and dot predict and supply test data instead this time and this will give Y prediction from the test data.
So what do we do with this?
So this value and this value.
We can measure the error between the prediction value and and a label.
So for example, so
training MSC or error for the training data is going to be MSC of Y true value for the training label, so which is this one, and the Y prediction value from the training data from this one.
So that's going to be our train error.
So for example this one.
And we can calculate similarly MSA for test data.
So MSA test TE is going to be MSA y test the true value and then the y prediction from the test data.
And this value is this for example.
So it's very common that the test error is a slightly larger than the train error.
Or if the data were pretty homogeneous and your model is doing well then train error and test error could be similar value.
We'll say later that if my model is overparameterized, then it doesn't do very well in the test data.
And it's an important way to figure out whether my model is overparameterized or not.
So we'll talk about that later.
In summary, we talked about how we determine the coefficients.
So we talked about least squares method.
method, which minimizes the residual sum of squares.
So we talked about what the RSS is, what the mean squared error is, and bunch of other error metrics.
And we also talked about the goodness of the model fit.
So we talked about R squared and how R squared is derived.
So we derived it using RSS and TSS.
And we also talked about some things that we need to be careful when we interpret the R squared value.
We also talked about significance of the coefficients.
So we talked about standard error of the coefficients, how they are derived or can be determined.
And then we talked about t-score and the p-value and hypothesis testing to say whether the coefficients values are significant or not.
And then we talked about confidence intervals as well.
And lastly, we talked about how to measure the error for training data and test data and how to compare them.
And that's it for the simple linear regression.
And in the next video, we're going to talk about what happens when we add more model complexity such as higher order terms or other features into the model.