In this video, we're going to talk about feature selection method and things to consider when we select features.
So last time, we tried to fit the model that has all the features inside and found that some of the coefficients were not significant.
So after removing those, we tried again and found that the coefficients are significant, but still we had some linearly dependent features in it.
So it's a lot of manual process to figure out which features to select.
So instead of doing that, we're going to introduce some method that automatically selects the features.
So the first method is called the forward selection, which add the feature one by one by looking at the one that maximizes the R-squared value.
So the add feature that maximizes the R-squared value, and that's the forward selection.
And another method is called the backward selection, which starts from the full model.
So by full model, I mean there are all the features inside the model already.
And remove the one feature that has maximum p-value.
So remove xj that has maximum p-value and we repeat this process until we reach the tolerance of the p-value or stop character.
Another good method is called a mixed selection which combines the forward selection and backward selection.
Which means that we add some feature that maximize the R-squared first and then fit the new model and inspect the result and see if there are
coefficients that are insignificant and if there are insignificant coefficients, just remove the features.
And then we add another feature again and then inspect the result and remove all the features that have large p-values and so on.
So let's compare the result.
So for selection gives this result that it adds a square for living first and then latitude and view and grade and so on.
And it doesn't have a stock criteria so we're gonna just fit all of them to the last feature.
And then this is result from the backward selection.
It starts from the full model and then it removes one by one.
So it first removed the floors and then secure-floor lot, second and sales months removed and so on all the way to the top.
And the year built was the last one that was removed.
But as you can see, the feature importance are the orders are very different from the floor selection because the floor selection cares about the R-squared value whereas the backward selection cares about the .
p-value and as you can imagine the mix selection resembles the four selection result.
However, it stops at some point.
So because it also look at the maximum r squared, the order orders are pretty similar to four selection, but then at some point adding another feature will lead always have a p value that's larger than certain criteria, so it stops there.
So actually practically mix selection is a good way to use.
as a feature selection.
So here is the result of the correlation matrix after we select the features from mixed selection.
So good news is that now we don't have the linearly dependent feature such as such as a square foot above.
These are gone, but still we see large correlation values between the features.
So let's talk about correlated features.
Why do they occur?
So high correlation among features may occur from different regions.
One of them would be redundant information.
So when the features are linearly dependent on each other, the information is redundant and they may have a high correlation.
And when there is an underlying effect such as confounding or causality, the features may be highly correlated.
So for example, ice cream sales and the sharks attack.
They have nothing to do with each other.
However, they can be caused by hot weather.
So, hot weather here is called confounding and then because of this confounding, ice cream sales and then sharks attack, they will have a high correlation in the data.
And the example of causality is heart disease can lead to heart attack and diabetes doesn't cause heart attack directly, but it can cause a heart disease, some type of heart disease and then cause a heart attack.
So when we look at the diabetes and then heart attack, they may look highly correlated.
And in some cases, just the variables are correlated in nature.
So for example, number of bedrooms and the size of house, they don't cause each other.
They don't have confounding.
However, they are just correlated.
So they may have high correlation.
So we mentioned that it is problematic when there are highly correlated features.
And why is that?
When the predictors are highly correlated, the coefficient estimate becomes very inaccurate.
And also, the interpretation of the coefficient.
as a variable contribution to the response becomes inaccurate.
So when there is a high correlation between features more than 0.7, we consider it's problematic.
And this is especially called collinearity when two features are very similar to each other.
Like we saw previously in the pair plot that the distribution of the data was very skinny between feature 1 and feature 2, for example, then they are very collinear.
Well, it's not always possible to detect the collinearity using correlation metrics.
Because if there are multiple variables that are involved in the collinearity, they may look like okay in the correlation matrix.
However, they could be still collinear.
And this special case is called the multicollinearity.
So beside the correlation matrix, variance inflation factor is a better way to detect this multicollinearity.
So VIF is defined by this formula.
The VIF of a coefficient beta i.
is 1 over 1 minus R squared value of this fitting and this fitting is actually not fitting the target variable Y but fitting that variable Xi using all other variables.
So using other variables that are not this one and we are fitting the model and we're gonna get the R squared value and we can get the VIF value.
So if the VIF value is larger than 5 in general,
or sometimes 10, it means that there is strong multicollinearity.
So let's have a look which variables had multicollinearity in the original model that we had all the features in it.
So clearly, square foot living, square foot above, square foot basement, they are linearly dependent each other.
So they show strong multicollinearity.
And then after we have a mixed selection, some of the redundant features are gone.
For example, this one is gone.
And let's inspect.
Square-foot living has still high VIF value, but it's much better than previous one because one of the dependent feature was gone.
And I think that was the only one that was bad here.
All right, but when we see the correlation matrix, there are still some highly correlated features.
Like for example this one.
So let's remove these highly correlated features.
after the mixed selection.
And when we remove those variables with a very high correlation to the square foot living, we end up with a much lower VIF value for square foot living because the collinearity is gone.
Here are some things to consider when we select features.
So we talked about model fitness.
Four selection gives a maximum model fitness by adding one features at a time.
And also we talked about removing variables with the insignificant coefficients.
So backward selection was good at this.
And if we combine this, we can have mixed selection.
We also talked about some problems that may occur when you have a multi-core linearity.
And we haven't talked about this, so let's have a look.
So here is a graph that shows the performance of each model.
This is including intercepts.
So this is just an intercept and this model is intercept 1.
feature and so on all the way to 14 feature plus intercept.
So it shows here.
And this star represents the model performance after we removing the variables with the high correlation.
So when we remove the highly correlated features, they may have a better estimation of the coefficient value and then better interpretation.
However, it can have some less performance.
And another thing that we can think about is that do we need all these 14 features?
It seems that the model complexity 6 or 7 gives a efficient result.
This is still a less performance than having 14 features.
However, it's good enough.
So we can consider that as well.
And by looking at the VIF of this six feature model, it has a pretty good VIF as well.
So here is all the results from the models that we considered so far.
So again, this number of features include the inner set.
So it's actually 19 feature model plus one inner set.
And mix selection gives a 14 number of features selected and so on.
And then if we look at just the feature coefficient for square foot living, the coefficient values are all different.
All of them are statistically significant.
However, if you can see the coefficient values, they are very different.
In particular, this model removed all the features that are highly correlated to the square foot living.
Therefore, the coefficient value for square-foot living is more accurate and more interpretable.
So this means that when we increase square-foot living by 1, then the house price goes up by $313.
On the other hand, the coefficient value for square-foot living is lower in other models.
And that's because the other models still had other variables that were highly correlated to the square-foot living.
Therefore, the coefficient values are not accurate.
and all these correlated features, they kind of share the contribution to the house price.
Okay, so lastly, let's talk about what to do when there are interactions.
So what is interactions?
Interactions can happen when this coefficient is not constant, but is a function of some other variable, say x3.
So in that case, what we want to do is that we're going to have interaction term, so x1 times x3, and then assign another coefficient.
Let's say beta and then add to the model.
And not only this, we can also do all the combinations such as adding x1 times x2, x2 times x3 and all combinations.
And we can also have a higher order terms, something like that.
In that case, we have infinite menu of features and we don't want to do that.
But however, we can just choose the order.
Maybe the maximum order is just one feature times another.
and then we can add them up.
Then we have a problem of how to select all these many combination features.
Again, we're going to apply the same method that we talked about before.
So, mixed selection method is a good way to do that.
One thing that is a little different from the previous case is that when we have this interaction term, then we must include also β1x1 plus β3x3
And sometimes you might see these coefficient values may not be significant.
However, we should still include these terms in order to have this term.
So with that difference, having interaction terms in the model is the same as having multiple features in the model.