Machine learning, we mentioned that machine learning several times during the talk about data science
So machine learning is part of data science and it is also a subfield of artificial intelligence
It focuses on learning algorithms and building models and training them on the data
Machine learning consists of different types of learning, such as supervised learning, unsupervised learning, or reinforcement learning
Many machine learning models, they are coming from statistical learning
In industry, machine learning engineers can develop and test machine learning models and design machine learning experiments
And in intersection, when the AI algorithm is learning from the data, it is called machine learning
And particularly, if it deals with complex data with neural network architecture, it is called deep learning
And here is the Google trend on the term on machine learning and software engineering
Alright, that already sounds like ML is very cool
Machine learning is also a key component in Internet of Things
Smart sensors and smart devices produce a lot of data, and also machine learning plays a key role in analyzing those data
Here are some few examples of machine learning tasks
So brief review of machine learning problems
And we're going to focus on supervised learning